A Finding Aid to the Don Seiler Papers, circa 1930-2020, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Don Seiler papers
circa 1930-2020
Archives of American Art
Seiler, Don, 1928-2000
AAA.seiledon
Archival Resource Key
3 Linear feet
The papers of Don Seiler measure 3.0 linear feet and date from circa 1930 to 2020. The papers document Seiler's career as an artist through correspondence with family and friends; diaries containing recollections of his early life and time serving during World War II, and some recollections of Seiler by family and friends in the years following his death; and artwork consisting of sketches and sketchbooks.
Biographical / Historical
Don Seiler (1928-2000) was a sculptor and painter in Miami and Ona, Florida. Seiler was born in Miami Beach, Florida in 1928. He began his studies at the Art Students League in 1945 before taking a hiatus to enlist in the Army's 11th Airborn Division that same year. Following World War II he completed his studies at the Art Students League, and he returned to Miami to open his studio. Seiler died in 2000.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1971-2001 (1.1 linear feet; Box 1, 4)
Series 2: Diaries, 1974-2020 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 3: Artwork, circa 1930-1996 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 3-7, OV 8-9)
Scope and Contents
The papers of Don Seiler measure 3.0 linear feet and date from circa 1930 to 2020. The papers document Seiler's career as an artist through correspondence with family and friends; diaries containing recollections of his early life and time serving during World War II, and some recollections of Seiler by family and friends in the years following his death; and artwork consisting of sketches and sketchbooks.
Correspondence consists primarily of letters to family and friends, including Maria Seiler and Lance Seiler. Also included are letters to Ralph Knutsen and letters related to a book on OnaLand. Scattered among the correspondence are some photographs of sculptures and some sketches.
Diaries consist of some loose leaf diary entries and two diaries primarily written by Seiler but also includeing some recollections from friends and family. Some of the diaries contain entries in which Seiler reminisces on his time serving during World War II. Also included among the diaries is a biographical binder consisting of some correspondence, photographs of Seiler's artwork, documents related to Seiler's death, and some recollections on his life by friends.
Artwork consists of sketches and sketchbooks documenting Seiler's distinctive visual language for depicting human and animal figures. Included are preparatory sketches for significant public art projects including his statue of former NFL quarterback Y.A. Tittle sited at Atlantic High School in Port Orange, Florida and the statue of a swimmer commissioned by the International Swimming Hall of Fame to stand outside its Florida headquarters.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2021 by Maria Seiler, Don Seiler's daughter-in-law.
Sculptors -- Florida; Painters -- Florida; Drawings; Sketchbooks; Diaries; World War, 1939-1945
- Correspondence, 1971-2001; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1, 4
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters to family and friends, including Maria Seiler and Lance Seiler. Also included are letters to Ralph Knutsen and letters related to the book on OnaLand. Scattered among the correspondence are some photographs of sculptures and some sketches.
  Arrangement
  Correspondence was housed in a number of binders with general range dates and remains filed in original order. Correspondence with Marie and Lance Seiler can be found in separate named folders, but also within the chronological folders.
  - Correspondence, 1971-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, circa 1976-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1982-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1989-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, circa 1990-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ralph Knutsen, 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Lance Seiler, 1986-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Maria Seiler, 1995-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - OnaLand Letters, 1985-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - OnaLand Letters, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Diaries, 1974-2020; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Diaries consist of some loose leaf diary entries and two diaries primarily written by Seiler but also includeing some recollections from friends and family. Some of the diaries contain entries in which Seiler reminisces on his time serving during World War II. Also included among the diaries is a biographical binder consisting of some correspondence, photographs of Seiler's artwork, documents related to Seiler's death, and some recollections on his life by friends.
  - Diary Entries, 1975-1978, 2008-2020; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Binder, 1974-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- Artwork, circa 1930-1996; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 3-7, OV 8-9
  Artwork consists of sketches and sketchbooks documenting Seiler's distinctive visual language for depicting human and animal figures. Included are preparatory sketches for significant public art projects including his statue of former NFL quarterback Y.A. Tittle sited at Atlantic High School in Port Orange, Florida and the statue of a swimmer commissioned by the International Swimming Hall of Fame to stand outside its Florida headquarters.
  - Sketches, circa 1968-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sketches, 1978-1992; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 8)
  - Sketches, 1978-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Sketches, 1980-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sketches, 1981-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sketches, circa 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, 1982-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, 1986-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Sketches, 1992-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Sketches, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 9)
  - Sketches, circa 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, 1981-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbooks, 1981-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)